Xavier University Institutional Anniversary Celebrations collection
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Institutional Anniversary Celebrations collection
1890-2006
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)
3.2 linear feet (7 boxes)
This collection consists of materials which commemorate various anniversaries celebrated by Xavier University. Anniversaries have been celebrated in 1890 (St. Xavier College Golden Anniversary), in 1931 (the 100th anniversary of the Athenaeum, the progenitor of Xavier University), in 1940 (the 100th Anniversary of the Jesuits forming St. Xavier College and the 400th Anniversary of the founding of the Society of Jesus), in 1956 (the 125th Anniversary of the founding of the Athenaeum (1831)), in 1976 as part of a campus celebration of the American Bicentennial, in 1981 (the 150th Anniversary of the founding of the Athenaeum), and in 2006 (the 175th Anniversary of the founding of the Athenaeum).
XUA-88
History of Anniversary Celebrations
Xavier University celebrated major anniversaries in 1890 (St. Xavier College Golden Anniversary); 1931 (the 100th anniversary of the Athenaeum, the progenitor of Xavier University); 1940 (the 100th Anniversary of the Jesuits forming St. Xavier College and the 400th Anniversary of the founding of the Society of Jesus); 1956 (the 125th Anniversary of the founding of the Athenaeum (1831)); 1976 as part of a campus celebration of the American Bicentennial, in 1981 (the 150th Anniversary of the founding of the Athenaeum); and 2006 (the 175th Anniversary of the founding of the Athenaeum).
Not specified
Scope and Content
This collection consists of materials which were created as part of various Xavier University anniversary celebrations. Materials include correspondence, programs, meeting minutes, brochures, and news clippings from 1890-2006.
Not specified
Statement of Arrangement
This collection is divided into seven series, as follows: Series I. 1890 Golden Jubilee of St. Xavier College (1840-1890) Series II. 1931 Centennial of the Founding of the Athenaeum (1831) Series III. 1940 Centennial of St. Xavier College (1840-1940) and the Jesuit Quadricentennial (1540-1940) Series IV. 1956 125th Anniversary of Xavier University (1831-1956) Series V. 1976 Bicentennial of the American Revolution on Xavier's Campus Series VI. 1981 150th Anniversary of Xavier University (1831-1981) Series VII. 2006 175th Anniversary of Xavier University (1831-2006)
Separated Material
Photographs for the 1940 Centennial are found in the photograph collection, numbers 12312 through 12339.
Related Material
Additional information on anniversary celebrations can be found in the Xavier University student newspaper.
XUA-56, Xavier University Capital Gifts Campaigns collection, Special Collections and University Archives, Xavier University, Cincinnati, Ohio.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research use.
Acquisition Information
These materials have been acquired from various sources.
Accruals
XUA2017-001
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)-- Anniversaries, etc.; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio) -- History
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I. 1890 Golden Jubilee of St. Xavier College (1840-1890)
  - 50th Anniversary of the Arrival of Jesuits in Cincinnati, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This folder contains letters and programs commemorating the the Golden Jubilee of St. Xavier College as well as a letter signed by Archbishop William Henry Elder of Cincinnati.
- Series II. 1931 Centennial of the Founding of the Athenaeum (1831-1931), 1926; 1930-1931
  - Correspondence, Records, 1926-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    This folder contains mainly correspondence. The signatures of President Herbert Hoover and Robert A. Taft are included.
  - Brochures, Announcements, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    This folder includes the Centennial Ball program.
- Series III. 1940 Centennial of St. Xavier College (1840-1940) and the Jesuit Quadricentennial (1540-1940), 1936-1943; undated
  - Summary of Events, 1940; undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    This folder includes a proclamation by the Mayor of Cincinnati James Garfield Stewart.
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This folder includes the edited manuscript "The Cross in the Valley" by John E. Reardon, S.J.. This work was written for the Xavier Centennial in commemoration of 100 years of Jesuit presence in Cincinnati.
  - 1940 Planning Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    This folder contains correspondence and meeting minutes.
  - Correspondence, 1936-1943; undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mass for Alumni, 1940; undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    This folder includes correspondence and the program of the Jesuit Quadricentennial / Xavier Centennial. It also includes information on the Mass for Alumni held on September 22, 1940.
  - Mass for Students, 1940; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    This program includes information on the Mass for Students held on September 27, 1940. The folder also includes the Program of the Jesuit Quadricentennial / Xavier Centennial.
  - Mass for the Public, 1940-1941; undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This folder includes correspondence, the leaflet missal for the student Mass of Thanksgiving held in the Xavier Fieldhouse on September 29th, 1940, and other materials.
  - Mass for Students Correspondence, 1940; undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    This folder contains correspondence relating to the Mass for Students held on September 29, 1940.
  - Commencement (6/5/1940) and Homecoming (11/2/1940) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    This folder includes correspondence and other materials relating to the Commencement program held June 5, 1940 and also the Xavier Homecoming held on November 2, 1940.
  - Centennial Dinner, 1940; undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    This folder contains correspondence about the Centennial Dinner held on November 24, 1940.
  - Centennial Pageant, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    This folder contains correspondence and other information concerning the Centennial Pageant held on April 10, 1940. Included is the text of the pageant which traces 400 years of Jesuit history and 100 years of Jesuit presence in Cincinnati.
  - Special Events, 1940; undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    This folder contains materials from various Centennial events, including the Xavier production of "Murder in the Cathedral" by T.S. Eliot, the Writers Contest, and the Centennial on radio.
  - Universal Jesuit Alumni Sunday, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    This folder includes correspondence, lists, and printed materials relating to the Universal Jesuit Alumni Sunday held on March 23, 1941.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    This folder contains newspaper articles about the 1940 anniversary.
- Series IV. 1956 125th Anniversary of Xavier University (1831-1956), 1955-1957; undated
  - Brochures, Celebration Preparation Materials, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    This folder includes a collection of informational materials "Manual for Press, Radio, TV: Anniversary Events, 125th Anniversary, Xavier University: Founder's Day (October 17), Anniversary Symphony Concert (November 20) and Other Events" published by the Office of Public Relations, Xavier University.
  - Planning Committee Minutes, 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Planning Committee Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Brochures, Pamphlets, 1956; undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    This folder contains spiral bound collections of the following publications: "Xavier University: Vidit Mirabilia Magna, 125 Years of Unchanging Vision (1831-1956)" by Paul L. O'Connor, S.J., "Institute of Hispanic Studies, Xavier University," "Xavier University 125th Anniversary Concert," and "Xavier University... an Introduction." The later publication is a view book of the university.
  - Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra Concert, 1956; undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    This folder contains correspondence, notes and the concert program for the Xavier University 125th Anniversary Concert performed by the Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra and held at the Xavier Fieldhouse on November 20, 1956.
  - Symphony Concert Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 3-A, Folder 1)
  - Symphony Concert Piano Scores, 1956 (Box 3-A, Folder 2)
    This folder contains piano scores to Felix Labunski's Xaveriana (Fantasy for Two Pianos and Orchestra), which piece was performed at the 1956 Xavier University Anniversary concert.
  - Symphony Concert Orchestral Scores, 1956 (Box 3-A, Folder 3)
    This folder contains orchestral scores to Felix Labunski's Xaveriana (Fantasy for Two Pianos and Orchestra), which piece was played as part of the 1956 Xavier Anniversary concert.
  - Founder's Day Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    This folder contains correspondence concerning the Founder's Day event held September 17, 1956.
  - O'Connor Address to Newcomen Society, 1955-1956; undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    This folder contains materials related to the 1956 dinner of the Newcomen Society at which the President of Xavier University Paul L. O'Connor gave the address "Xavier University: Vidit Mirabilia Magna: 125 Years of Unchanging Vision (1831-1956)." The text of the address, published in pamphlet format, is included.
  - Undying Troth by James Powell, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    This folder contains the photocopied manuscript "Undying Troth: a Chronicle of Xavier University" written by James Powell. Powell wrote this unpublished history to observe the 125th Anniversary of Xavier's founding.
    This manuscript has been digitized. Please contact the archives staff.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1956; undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    This folder contains newspaper clippings and several copies of the Special 125th Anniversary Issue of the Xavier University News.
- Series V. 1976 Bicentennial of the American Revolution on Xavier's Campus, 1975-1976; undated
  - Brochures, Correspondence, 1975-1976; undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    This folder includes correspondence, brochures and other printed materials related to Xavier's celebration of the nation's 200th birthday in 1976. Included in the folder is the publication "Bicentennial America: Window on the Past, Present, and Future" by Roger A. Fortin of Xavier's History Department.
- Series VI. 1981 150th Anniversary of Xavier University (1831-1981), 1978-1982
  - Planning, Calendar of Events, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    This folder contains various printed materials concerning planning and publicity of the 150th Anniversary of Xavier University.
  - Healy Keynote Address, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    This folder contains the text of Timothy S. Healy, S.J.'s keynote address delivered on January 22, 1981 at the commemoration of Xavier's 150th Anniversary. Other printed materials related to this address are also included.
  - Symphony Concert and New College of Business Building, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    This folder contains the 1981-1982 Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra concert program sponsored by Xavier University to celebrate its 150th year. It also contains information on the building and dedication of the College of Administration building.
  - Anniversary Celebration Publications, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    This folder contains programs associated with the 150th Anniversary celebration. Also included are copies of the publication Xavier Communique (October, 1981) which has an article about the celebration.
  - Inaugural Lecture of Chair of Interreligious Ecumenical Studies, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    This folder contains the lecture by Rabbi Alfred Gottschalk "What Ecumenism Means to a Jew." This lecture was given as part of an Academic Convocation to honor Dr. Gottschalk and to recognize the institution of the first Chair in Interreligious-Ecumenical studies. The convocation happened on April 7, 1981.
  - Academic Convocations Lecture Series: Modes of Understanding Human Existence, 1981; undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    This folder contains various publicity pieces, brochures, and other materials related to the March 23-27, 1981 lecture series "Modes of Understanding Human Existence." Speakers in this series included Fritjof Capra, James Merrill, Mortimer Adler, Julian Jaynes, and Walter Burghardt, S.J..
  - Proclamations, Bennish Xavier History, Speakers Service, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    This folder contains various proclamations honoring Xavier University on its 150th Anniversary. Also included is information on the book "Continuity and Change: Xavier University, 1831-1981" by Lee Bennish, S.J. which was published to mark the anniversary. A 1981 publication "Speakers from Xavier University" is also included.
  - Newspaper Clippings and Miscellaneous, 1979-1981; undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    This folder contains newspaper clippings covering the Xavier 150th Anniversary. It includes also miscellaneous materials such as postcards, bumper stickers, and blank stationery.
  - Correspondence, Final Reports, 1981-1982; undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series VII. 2006 175th Anniversary of Xavier University (1831-2006), 2005-2006; undated
  - Overview and Steering Committee Minutes, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Opening Event and Commencement, 2006; undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    This folder includes various scripts from the January 9, 2006 opening event. Also included is the commencement program for May 13, 2006.
  - Jesuit Seminar and Alumni Reunion Events, 2006; undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    This folder includes a PowerPoint printout from a campus book discussion on "The Catholic University as Promise and Project" by Michael J. Buckley, S.J.. Also included are various materials concerning Alumni Reunion events for 2006.
  - Academic Day and Kolvenbach Dinner, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    This folder includes various brochures and correspondence concerning Academic Day held October 3, 2006. Also included is the text of the speech given that day by Peter Hans Kolvenbach,S.J., Superior General of the Society of Jesus, entitled "The Service of Faith in a Religiously Pluralistic World." Also included are materials from the 175th Anniversary Dinner held also on October 3, 2006. The script from a short play "To See Great Wonders" which was given that evening is included.
  - Founders' Day, 2006; undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    This folder includes the program for Founders' Day held on September 29, 2006.
  - Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra Concert, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    This folder includes materials associated with the October 27-28, 2006 performances given by the Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra in which the 175th Anniversary of Xavier University was celebrated.
  - Living Longer Conference, 2006; undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    This folder contains materials concerning the Living Longer Conference of November 3, 2006. It was sponsored by Xavier University's College of Social Sciences, Health, and Education as part of Xavier's 175th Anniversary celebration.
  - Jesuit Education 175th Celebration Materials, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    This folder contains various materials relating to the November 30, 2006 event held jointly by Xavier University and St. Xavier High School to mark 175 years of Jesuit education in Cincinnati.
  - 2006 Events, 2005-2006 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    This folder contains information on various 175th Xavier Anniversary events and activities: Interfaith Community Forum (November 5, 2006), the program "Jesuit Education and the Classics" (November 4-6, 2005), anniversary banners in the Gallagher Student Center.
  - Varia, 2005-2006; undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    This folder contains various materials related to the Xavier 175th Anniversary: brochures, correspondence, an historical timeline, and a manuscript "In the Beginning" which gives a Xavier historical overview.